Hello, and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrdan.
And today we're going to be diving
into the world of organic chemistry.
Specifically, we're going to be looking
at how to name alkanes with branches.
Now, this is part of my organic,
introductory organic chemistry series.
So let's really go into how
we can start naming these.
So prior, alkanes and that there is
a very systematic way to doing these.
Now, with branches, which are
commonly known as substituents,
are parts that are breaking off the
main chain and can be a little bit
tricky when it comes to naming them.
The good thing is we're doing
this systematically, so it all
comes down to how many carbons are
there within a given chain, right?
So most of your different branches are
generally very small, typically they don't
go above 5 carbons, but it is possible
for you to even get larger than this.
So now when it comes to most, most of
these, right, if you think of the, of one
carbon alkane, you think methane, right?
Especially when you think of that alkane.
So whenever we're looking at these,
so the very first species is it,
you're just taking the prefix of
it, which is that meth part of it.
And then you're going to be
adding the essentially the suffix
of it, which is the YL ending.
Now, being that these
are alkyl chains, right?
We will always be using that,
that YL ending to denote that,
hey, we have a branch, or as I
mentioned before, a substituent.
So both names can be used in this case.
So methyl is for one carbon, and we
can continue to name the rest of them.
So two is going off eth, right?
Think of like ethane, ethanol,
all those different species.
We're going to keep that beginning prefix.
And then put the YL ending on it as well.
So I'm going to put these YLs here.
So we have ethyl, then we have
three carbons, which is propyl.
Then we have four carbons, which is butyl.
And then we have five
carbons, which is pentyl.
So it's taking that beginning
part of that name, right?
And this is something, if you're
taking organic chemistry, you need
to memorize these different endings.
They are going to be a huge
part when it comes to naming
structures, drawing structures,
and really diving into all these.
So let's go through this and do a how
to guide of exactly how to name them.
So first things first, when you are
naming these, you have to identify and
name what the longest carbon chain is.
So you have to be comfortable with
knowing your carbons from generally
from one to 10 when you're doing these.
Now, when I refer to the parent chain or
the longest carbon chain, This has to be
continuous carbons connected together.
So it has to be in one solid line
when you're going through it.
The second step is we're going
to be identifying all branches.
There's a number of ways
that you can try to do this.
You can circle them, you can underline
them, you put arrows on them, star them.
But you need to be able
to identify your branches.
Then you need to number your
carbons, so on your parent chain.
And you want to start on the
end that is closest to a branch.
And we're going to go through
examples to show this.
Then you want to give the
location and name each branch in
alphabetical order when we do this.
Sometimes you might have identical
branches as well, and we'll have to
fold in some special prefixes as well.
Let's take a look at our first examples
and use these steps to help us.
Alright, let's start with
the first carbon chain here.
So what we're going to be doing
first is naming and identifying
what our longest carbon chain is.
So one thing that I like to do is, if
you're really new at this, Is I try
to figure out and start it all of the
different ends that are possible and
what you are essentially doing in this
case is you're trying to see is like
what kind of different angles can you
go to try to connect these, right?
So if I go across, I can see that I
have 4 different carbons here, right?
So you got 1, you have 2, 3, 4.
So that's 1 possibility.
I could wrap around and go up and we
notice that, okay, this one's only.
Uh, three total carbons, so
that's a little bit shorter.
We could also go from maybe the
left hand side and go up, and we see
that's one, two, three, and four.
So there's different options that
are available, and they'll all
give you the same answer as long
as you pick the longest chain.
So let's go from the one that I
have here going across, that's
always the easiest thing to do.
We have four carbons
in this particular one.
So four carbons, that, we are
going to put that name down.
And that will be butane, right?
Butane is four carbons.
We have the ene ending to say
that's an alkene, bute meaning four.
Now the next step is trying to identify
all of the different parts, uh,
that are outside your parent chain.
So one thing I personally like to do is
I always maybe circle my parent chain.
So that way I can remember where exactly
it is, especially if you have a tendency
to forget or get lost while you're
doing it, it can serve as a reminder.
So that means there's one carbon
that is outside of it, right?
So this one here in green
is outside of that group.
So this is going to be our,
our substituent or our branch.
And now when we are numbering that
parent chain, we have to start
at the end that's closest to it.
So if you look up here,
right, what's closest?
Well if I do it on the right, I can
see I have one, two, three, four,
if I start from the right hand side.
Now we always want to give the lowest
number possible, so that's why we start
at the end that is closest to our branch.
So, now what is the name of that branch?
Well, if you remember from
before, you have one carbon.
One carbon was methyl.
So what we will do is we will number
its location, and then we will name it.
So it will be 2 methylbutane
will be the first name.
And that's how you would go about that.
Let's try another one.
Let's keep trying to work on these.
So I have another example
over here in the corner.
So how exactly would you do this?
Same idea as before.
You're trying to figure out what is the
longest possible chain as you're going
through all these different angles.
So you're gonna be, so the first
thing is most people will do
is they'll count across, right?
So if you do that, you can see we
have five carbons that are here.
That might be your longest.
What other options could there be?
We could do 4.
That's not longer.
We could do 5.
That's the same length, so that
should be the same molecule.
So when it comes to naming, so
it looks like 5 is your longest.
So 5, this is one of the ones that
goes off your geometric shapes.
So that would be pent for five.
And being that we are talking
about an alkane, it will have
that a N E ending or penting.
All right.
Now, what about numbering and naming them?
Well, when it comes to trying to
actually look at this parent chain here.
We want to make sure that we are numbering
from whatever part is closest to a branch.
So I just outlined it in orange
for us, and you can see that the
branch that's on the right hand
side is a little bit closer.
Keep in mind, you don't always
have to start from the right hand.
It just happens to be that I picked
one that was on this side, , so we
would start numbering over here.
So it'd be 1, 2, 3, 4, and then five.
Alright, so we have two of them, right?
And the thing that's about this is, oh,
wait, there was a little bit of a rule
with this, so let's take a look at that
real quick, is that when you have two of
them and they're identical, we have to
use these little prefixes that are here.
So, we had two methyl groups,
each one had one carbon each.
So being that they are identical,
we are going to use the di prefix.
to say where this is.
So let's take a look at what
this would look like and how
we would go about doing this.
Let's go back to the problem.
So this is one area that you want to
make sure that you do use that prefix.
So being that you have two of
them, one's at two, the other one
is at three, you will put a comma
to say where each one is located.
Even if they're on the same
carbon, you've got to include
the number for every single one.
Every branch has to have a number.
Now being that they're both methyl,
we are gonna use the dye prefix
and then we will say methyl.
So it'll be two three dimethyl.
Penting would be the complete
name for the structure.
So we break it down one at a time.
The two, three tells you the location
of it, wheres it, that dye tells
you that there's two of them and
that they're identical and that
methyl is at in methyls how many
carbons there are for those branches.
And pentane was the length of the chain.
Let's try another.
So if I have this one, once
again we gotta try to figure out
what's our longest chain, and
there might be multiple options.
It doesn't always have to go across.
So one thing is if I were to look
at this, right, if I go across
say 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, great.
Let's try a different way.
I do 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, That also works.
So this is one thing that you got
to keep in mind when you start
doing isomers that you have to
count every time you name them.
That's the best way to
try to figure them out.
So we see we have six is
most likely the longest.
So let's go through and do six,
six, they think hexagons, right?
So hexane would be the
name here for the parent.
So hexane is our longest.
And how about for fun, we'll number
it along the weird route here
where it wrapped around the ring.
It doesn't have to go along
the zigzag necessarily.
It just kind of makes it
a little bit different.
So when we're numbering this, we want
to try, our goal is to always give
more substituents a lower number.
Now when you look at this, you see
that, oh, well, I have two methyls
and That are both three, and I also
have an ethyl that is three as well.
So which one should you pick
when you're going through this?
That's a little bit harder.
So the thing is when you're
numbering these you always want
to give more a lower number.
Now, why am I saying that is because
if I start numbering from the right, I
can give two, or two methyls a three.
Versus, let's say if I go on the
other side, Notice how I can give
another branch a three as well.
Well, they both would
have a really low number.
So it's closest on both sides, but
you want to try to serve, serve the
common good, which one can serve
more substituents, more branches.
So being that you have Two branches.
You have one here, one here.
That can be two that you are helping.
All right.
We also have a branch
that's up here as well.
So we have another one that is here.
So why don't we maybe circle
each one just to kind of help
us guide our eyes for later.
So we got one, two, and then three.
Let's go through and name them.
So we know we have hexane.
Now what would come first in that name?
Well being that we have multiple
types, we alphabetize them in order.
So being that I have a two carbon branch,
this is what we refer to as an ethyl.
So we will label that, right, so we have
ethyl, and then we have our dimethyl
on the side, just like we did kind
of on the last prompt, but they're
both on the same carbon this time.
So ethyl would be first, so what we would
end up doing is being that's on number
four, We will say 4 methyl, and then we
have 2 methyls on the same spot, so that's
going to end up being 3 3, so it would
be another borotholin 3 dimethylhexane.
And that would be the complete
name for the structure.
So you're systematically going
through each of these structures.
Let's try another example.
So if I were to go through this
one, well, how exactly, where
should I start in numbering it?
There's all kinds of different pathways
you can realistically choose here.
So one thing is, well, you know, I
want to try to be close to branches.
So if I go one, two, three, 4, 5, 6, 7.
That's pretty long.
I go 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
Okay, that one's longer.
Can I do anything else?
Let's see if I go over here.
4, 5.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
It looks like 8 is our longest route.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to outline that, that pathway.
So that was 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 7, or 1, 8.
Sorry, sometimes counting is hard.
All right, so we're going to number those.
Now we want to give everything
the lowest number possible.
So we start from the right again.
We will happen to be closer to
our, uh, one of our branches.
And that's another thing to keep
in mind when you are trying to
number all these different alkanes.
You, uh, generally always want to make
sure that you're including all branches.
Try to make them as simple as possible
for yourself when you're doing this.
All right, so if we were to look
here at the first one, we have
one, two methyls, and then we
have another two carbon species,
which once again is another Ethyl.
So how would we go about numbering this?
First thing is name your parent chain.
What was 8?
Which is octane, right?
Octane as in the way
you drive for your car.
So we'll put octane, then in
alphabetical, what comes first?
Ethyl or methyl?
Well, E before M.
So what we will do is we will number that.
We have 5, ethyl.
And then we will put 3, 4, dimethyl
for our other, uh, branches.
And that is our entire name.
So it would be 5 ethyl 3, 4
dimethyl octane would be the
entire name for the species.
So when you're going through these,
just remember, find your longest carbon
chain, try to count from every end,
Name it, right, if you need to, put
them on flashcards, then afterwards
you're going to identify and number
the branches, and then you're going
to, when you're writing it out, you
write out your parent name, and then
put the location and the name of each
branch, put them in alphabetical order.
And don't forget about the prefixes,
right, if it's di tri and tetra
It just keeps taking practice.
So keep trying and you will get better.
Thank you so much for listening.
I hope that this video helped.
If it's your first time here, if you
haven't been here before, comment
below if you want to tell me all about
or have questions or hit that like
and subscribe button to the channel.
I really appreciate it.
Thank you all so much and
I'll see you all later.
Bye now.